<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Actes of the ambassage passed at the meatinge of the lordes and princes of Germany at Naumburg in Thuringe concerninge the matters there moued by Pope Pius the iiij. in the yeare of our Lord 1561 and the fyfth day of February item, the answere of the same lords and princes, geuen to the Popes nuntio vpon the eygth day of February / translated out of the Duch into English.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1561</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 11 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08049</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18412.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S2244</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">23189523</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 23189523</idno>
            <idno type="VID">26359</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08049)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 26359)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1800:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Actes of the ambassage passed at the meatinge of the lordes and princes of Germany at Naumburg in Thuringe concerninge the matters there moued by Pope Pius the iiij. in the yeare of our Lord 1561 and the fyfth day of February item, the answere of the same lords and princes, geuen to the Popes nuntio vpon the eygth day of February / translated out of the Duch into English.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By John Day, dwelling ouer Aldersgate, beneath S. Martins,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1561]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint date suggested by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁸.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  History --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:26359:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:26359:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE ACTES OF THE AMBAſſage PASSED AT THE meatinge of the Lordes and Princes of Germany at Naum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg in Thuringe concerninge the matters there moued by Pope Pius the <hi>iiij.</hi> in the yeare of our Lord. 1561. and the fyſth day of Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bruary.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item,</hi> The anſwere of the ſame Lords and Princes, geuen to the Popes Nuntio vpon the eygth day of Febru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary.</p>
            <p>¶ Tranſlated out of Duch into Engliſh.</p>
            <p>¶ Imprinted at London by John Day, dwelling ouer Alderſgate, beneath S. Martins.</p>
            <p>¶ Cum gratia &amp; priuilegio Regiae Maieſtatis.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:26359:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:26359:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The Summa of the matters moued by the Nuntio of Pope Pius the forth, at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meating of the Lords &amp; Princes of Germany at Nau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burge in Turinge the fyfth day of Februarij, in the yeare of oure Lorde. <hi>1561.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>The Popes Legate ſayd.<lb/>
               <q>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S ſone as the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes holynes was called to the gouen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of holy churche he by and by, according to his Paſtorall office &amp; Popedome, ſett all his thought and care howe to reforme, the euel and corrupt manners of lyfe, now vſed, that the fredome of the church, might once agayne be reſtored, &amp; all people reduced to the vnity of one faith. And
<pb facs="tcp:26359:3"/>foraſmuch as, to the reducing of good, &amp; putting away of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil ther can be found none o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther medicyne nor helpe, but by the kepinge of a generall Councell: he hath with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and wel aduſſed councell of his Cardinalls, by his full powre &amp; auctoritie geuen him of god, determined to hold an holy Councel, at Eſter, in the citie of Trient. And to thende that this may be knowen to al princes, that they alſo may take the like care, and in like manner do theyr diligence in councelling that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Duch na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion may haue peace &amp; quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, &amp; ioyning in care with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Popes holynes, they may to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether ſett to theyr helpinge hande, he hath of very loue &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:26359:3"/>good wil which he hath euer borne vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Duch nation, &amp; for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great deſire to ſeke their vnity, ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t furth vs his legats y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we in his name ſhuld proue &amp; moue euery Lord ſeuerally, pray, admoniſh, &amp; moſt erneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly aduertiſe, &amp; require them, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thei wil viſit this general cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cel, &amp; permit y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this his bleſſed care &amp; purpoſe may procead &amp; take effect. Foraſmuch as all matters therin ſhalbe quietly mildly &amp; peaceably handled, &amp; howſoeuer the matter falleth out, yt ſhalbe with lyke mild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes herd &amp; determined. For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> popes holynes in this, ſeketh none other thinge, but how y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church may again be brought to peace and tranquilitye.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>And to this ende the pope is
<pb facs="tcp:26359:4"/>is ready to giue vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces a free and ſuer ſaulfe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducte, in all the beſt and in as a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple &amp; large maner as euer yet hath bene' geuen, or els may be inue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted to be geuen. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> popes holines beſecheth and admoniſheth, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Prin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces will, all &amp; euery one ſende their Ambaſſadours with ful aucthority thether, that thro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we theyr diligence, after the Schiſme (wherein are as ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny ſondry kindes of religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as good Imaginations, &amp; ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dry goſpels as teachers) be pacified, the church may a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain be reſtored to her former bewtie, one faith may be hol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>den in al countreyes, and one God of all men in all places worſhipped.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:26359:4"/>
               <q>VVhat more is in oure Ambaſſage (ſayd the Legate) it ſhall be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared by my felowe Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſioner.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Then ſpake the ſame as here after foloweth.<lb/>
               <q>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Noble Princes, foraſmuch as the pops holynes hath geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs both one commaundement, I thinck it not neadful to repete thoſe things that my felowe Commiſſioner hath propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded concerning the miſerable eſtate of the church. For euery man may openly ſee, to what myſery the mater wil growe, &amp; what wil be the ende ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. For one miſery ſpringeth after another, and it ſhall at laſt giue an open way to the
<pb facs="tcp:26359:5"/>enemy of chriſtendome, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroi y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> welth It were very nedeful therfor to preue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t this miſchief, this imminent peril requireth ſpeady redres this councelleth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good opor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunitie of tyme &amp; goodnes of Pope Pius, whoſe full ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour good meaning &amp; dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce alſo is to be regarded. There was neuer a better oportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to making of peace, nor ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer can ther be a better the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is at this preſent, when al Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten realmes are in quiet, &amp; one pope is geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of God, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth his ſinguler good will &amp; fauour toward y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Potentats, &amp; ſeketh the ſaluacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of theyr ſouls, and holly endeuoureth hiſelf to bring y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church again to vnity peace and quietnes.</q>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:26359:5"/>
               <head>The anſwer of the lords &amp; Princes of Germany geuen to the Popes Nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tio, in the Diet of Nau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>burg in Thuring, in Febr. An <hi>1561.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He right high excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and noble Lords and Princes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayn Empire here preſent, &amp; alſo Thambaſſadours &amp; coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cellers of thoſe that be abſent hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded to geue this anſwere, vnto your wurds &amp; meſſage, done &amp; preſented be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>for theyr moſt honorable lord ſhips and Princelye graces. Namelye, that theyr Noble Lordſhips and Princely gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces doubt nothing at all, that many men wel learned, wyſe &amp; fearing God, at all tymes &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:26359:6"/>among al people of the whole worlde &amp; that of longe tyme haue wiſhed, that the Chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> churche might be brought to ſome better eſtate and ſtaye, &amp; euen now at this tyme make thei deuout and harty prayer with ſighing vnto God that once at the laſt the pure doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine may be reſtored and ſett vp, and the horible miſuſes, which haue bene brought in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Church, may thorow a Chriſtian reformacion ceaſe &amp; be put away. Whiche deſire of reformation, &amp; prayer to God for the ſame doubteles ought as well to be in the Romiſhe Popes who ſo longe &amp; many yeres haue taken vpon them with ſo great po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pe the name
<pb facs="tcp:26359:6"/>&amp; title of the Churche. But to what purpoſe? Nameli, with luſt to reigne ouer other, to ſet kigdown &amp; realmes at debat, &amp; to bring in by heapes, into the church manifeſt &amp; knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Idolatry, to maintaine euery Pope for his time their glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſe eſtate rather the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to helpe &amp; refourme the abuſes of the churche, which thinge is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt to all honeſt &amp; goodher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Chriſtians, whiche thing alſo many wiſe &amp; ſage men, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> other wiſe haue ioyned &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federat them ſelues to the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe, dothe themſelfes acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg and confeſſe.</p>
               <p>But the forſaid noble lords &amp; princes here preſent &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadours of the lords abſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t
<pb facs="tcp:26359:7"/>wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der much of what prowd cuſtome or preſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptuouſe hope pope Pius y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iiij. preſumeth by this his meſſage to ſummone the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to a cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cel, or to apoit the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to come to Trie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Seing. it is not vnkno we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> both to y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> pope &amp; to you what religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eſtates of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> auſpurg confeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> holdeth &amp; vpon what occaſions they haue bene dryue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pelled to purg &amp; reforme their churches according to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> trewe doctrine of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpel, &amp; to ſeperate the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfs from y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> multitude y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> with thoppreſſion of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> trueth &amp; god<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly doctrine, ſeeke muche more their own gaine, then Chriſts glory. For the lords &amp; Princes pleaſur is, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the pope &amp; al that take his parte ſhall perfectlye know &amp; be aſſured, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg
<pb facs="tcp:26359:7"/>not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> power or au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctority of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> romiſh ſea. And y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei know it for an vndouted trueth by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> teſtimony both of Gods law &amp; mans, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth not of right to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Romiſh pope to apoint a general cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel. For y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſelf &amp; ſame ꝑſon, of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all diuiſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; ichnine in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> church hath come, which alſo horribl<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ugneth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nifeſt trueth, ſhuld take vpon hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dignity &amp; office of a iudg, to determine y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> matters in con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trouerſy, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wit of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be it neuer ſo ſimple, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of Gods law, doth vs to vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de that it is vnright.</p>
               <p>Furthermore theyr honora<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble eſtats &amp; lordſhips erneſtly ſay, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theyr graciouſe honors ar vnfre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly vſed, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this your talke
<pb facs="tcp:26359:8"/>&amp; maſſage done vnto them: as who ſaith to men y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> know not what their faith is: but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ther are, as many Goſpels as tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, &amp; as many religions, as mens good meaninges. For their high honors, haue not only made a pure &amp; cleare Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of their faith, whiche thei deliuered to Charles the v. at Auſpurg in the yeare of our Lord. 1530. but alſo they haue ſince y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> time ſett furthe &amp; declared y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame trueth of god<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly doctrine, &amp; is welſet furth by mani other writigs which are euery where to be ſene.</p>
               <p>But in what errours y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Churche is at this tyme drowned, &amp; with what abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable miſuſes &amp; Idolatriſh
<pb facs="tcp:26359:8"/>inuentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of men, the doctrine of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpel is there oppreſſed, yea ſo farre: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is more lyke an Heythneſſe then a Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, is ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the manifolde co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plaint of all the worlde. And foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muche as the noble Lords &amp; Princes of Duchland, no<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> as men falle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in errour, not of fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward &amp; conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nouſe minde, nor nor new fangelled lightnes, but by the erneſt and ſtraight co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement of God, be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled to departe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh churche, they are purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vpon the ſame grounde &amp; commaundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſo to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue &amp; can not ſuffer that the pope ſhal make or appoint any law for them. For they acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg
<pb facs="tcp:26359:9"/>none other power or ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, then their Emperour Ferdinando, whoſe Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dours are here and haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared vnto vs, what theyr hop<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; purpoſe is as concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning a general councell.</p>
               <p>¶ Laſtly as concerning your own Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, theyr hye honours and graces, wolde ye ſhield be thus perſwaded, that yf ye had not brought this meſſage fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Romiſh Pope, they wolde haue wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comed you, as ſuche as come of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable Venetyan howſe, &amp; haue ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed to yow all louing and gentil inter ſaynment, ther by to declare in ſompart theyr frendly good will to that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable regiment of Venice, and alſo to doo you vnderſtande, that they iudge you wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy bothe prayſe &amp; theyr fauour for your hono<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rable behaueour, high prude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, and wyſdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:26359:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
